Preliminary Inventory to the David Dean Barrett Papers, 1933-1970
Hoover Institution Archives
David Dean Barrett Papers,
1933-1970
48005
Barrett, David D. (David Dean), 1892-1977.
1 manuscript box, 4 envelopes, 1 album box, 2 phonorecords, memorabilia. (1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Manuscripts of writings, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and phonorecords, relating to the Dixie Mission and the military situation in China during World War II. Includes a coat worn in China by Colonel Barrett.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
United States--Army--Officers.; United States--Observer Mission to Yenan, 1944-1945.; Communism.; Communism--China.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; China.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; Phonorecords.
Biography
Colonel, U.S. Army; chief of the U.S. Dixie Mission to Chinese communist forces, 1944.
Scope and Content of Collection
Manuscripts of writings, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and phonorecords, relating to the Dixie Mission and the military situation in China during World War II. Includes a coat worn in China by Colonel Barrett.
Container List
- Biographical information. Article on David D. Barrett, San Francisco Chronicle, 1970 December 13 (Box 1., Folder 1)
- Correspondence (Folder 2)
  - Letter, Lancelot Giles to David D. Barrett, 1933 November 2, regarding the Boxer Rebellion and a particular incident. Typescript
  - Letter, David D. Barrett to Dr. Currie, 1941 February 12, regarding the military and economic situation in China, as well as communist activities. Typescript
  - Letter, Nelson T. Johnson to David D. Barrett, 1944 April 29, regarding the situation in China (Chiang, Japanese, etc.). Typescript
  - Letter, John P. Welch to General Gibbins, 1937 August 24, regarding Peiping and Tientsin (China)
- Instructions to Col. Barrett from the U.S. Army. Forces in China Theater, regarding the mission of intelligence detachment sent into the area under control of the Chinese communists. Typescript (Folder 3)
- Manuscript entitled "The Dixie Mission" regarding a U.S. Army Observer Group that was sent from the China-Burma-India Theater Headquarters, in Chungking, to establish liaison with the Chinese Communists in Yenan, Shensi Province, then headquarters of the Chinese Communists, 1944 (110 pages) (Folder 4-5)
- Printed matter (Folder 6)
  - Cartoons (positive photostats) of "American Spy Activities" drawn by Miao-ti and Chao Chin-fang, relating to Col. Barrett's spy activities. Published in Peiping newspapers in August or September 1951
  - Copy of article "A U.S. Spy Ring in New China" by Adam Lapin, Our World, 1961 October 5
- Photographs (Photo file Photo file)
  - 22 prints plus 8 duplicates depicting activities of the U.S. Army Observer Group in Yenan, China, 1944 (Folder A)
  - 1 photo of Armed Services attaches and officers of the Foreign Legation Guards. Peking, 1928 (Folder mB)
  - 1 photo of Yen Hsi-shan. Taipei, 1951 (Folder mC)
  - Photograph albums and parts of albums, primarily in China and Taiwan, 1944-1950 (Folder fD)
  - 1 print of David Barrett; 11 prints of David Barrett and others; 2 prints of General Douglas MacArthur; 1 print of President and Mme. Chiang Kai-Shek; 1 print of Pres, Chiang Kai-shek; 8 unidentified prints, undated (Box E)